Men are more conservative than women
男性比女性更保守
more traditional
更传统
the second
第二个
highly educated
教育程度高的
less educated than
比教育程度低的
less conservative
更不保守
Turning into an adult is an objective determination
转大人是一个客观的认定
or subjective determination
还是主观的认定
did you say
有没有说
Be an adult girl by the age of eighteen
到十八岁来个成年女
you become an adult
你就变成大人了
because they feel
因为他们觉得
This thing is a subjective determination
这个东西是一个主观认定
He needs some objective indicators
他要有一些的客观的指标
to match him
来配合他
what do you mean by making your own decision
你什么叫做自己做决定
own responsibility
自己负责任
This is relatively simple
这个是比较简单的
So everyone thinks this is not enough
所以大家觉得这个不能满足
I appreciate
我非常感谢
over the years
过去这么多年来
This plan
这个计划
Academia Sinica
主要是从中研院
main research plan
主体研究计划
and the Ministry of Science and Technology
还有科技部
Previous NSC support
以前的国科会的支持
and social institute
以及社会所
Only when the funds are available can it last until now
经费之时才能持续到现在
we want to know
我们想要知道
The growth trajectory of contemporary young people
当代年轻人的成长轨迹
the second
第二个
Timeline of our positioning
我们的定位的时程
from a life course perspective
是用一个生命历程取向来看
from early teens
从青少年初期
traced to
一直追踪到
his young adult stage
他年轻成人的阶段
The third
第三个
Of course we want to see
我们当然是想要看
Indigenous development model
本土化的發展模式
The pressure of entering a higher school
升學的壓力
Results of cram school, etc.
補習班的結果等等
Actually that's them
其實那才是他們
really a second way of life
真的是第二個生活方式
At the beginning there were about 5,000 people
一開始大概是五千餘位
face method
面法
so we are lucky
所以我們很幸運
From our more than 5,000 samples
可以從我們五千多位樣本中
find some
找到一些
Yeah, just retro and teen
對 就復古跟青少年
do some in-depth interviews
做一些深入訪談
so everyone can see
所以大家可以看到
Our sample is 2,000 years old
我們樣本是兩千年時
Country One and Country Three
國一和國三
The third year of the country was the last
當年的國三是最後
The last generation of candidates
末代考生 聯考的制度
Country one is the new system
國一是新的制度
under the new system
在新制下
in the top twenty-five percent
在前百分之二十五的
Chances of attending star high schools
上明星高中的機會
significantly high
顯著的高
So indeed reform
所以的確教改
yes bring some
是帶來一些
greater inequality
更大的不平等
family experience
家庭經驗
What we care about is a structure
我們在乎的是一個結構
a relationship
一個關係
parents divorce
父母離婚
In the end the impact on children
到底對子女的影響
what is it
又是什麼
Here I will give you a report
在這裡我跟大家做一個報告
College Graduation for Two-Parent Families
雙親家庭的大學畢業
relatively high ratio
比例比較高
non-two-parent family
非雙親家庭
Graduated from high school
高中職畢業的
relatively high ratio
比例比較高
so here
所以這裡面
There are some differences in education
就有一些教育程度的差異
Let's just say family structure
我們就說家庭結構
Is there any effect
有沒有什麼影響
we know low birth rates
我們知道低生率
this problem is serious
這個問題很嚴重
and marriage
而且婚姻
Phenomena included
包括的現象
It means that the society still does not accept out-of-wedlock children
意思就是社會還是不接受未婚生子
I remember when I was doing an interview
我記得我做一個訪談的時候
Respondents who were pregnant out of wedlock told me
未婚懷孕的受訪者跟我說
He doesn't even want to marry him
他其實都不想嫁給他
Because he thinks he can't get along with him, doesn't love each other
因為他覺得他跟他合不來 不相愛
Parents say I don't care if you love each other or not
父母說我不管你相不相愛
you hurry to get married
你趕快去結婚
divorce after childbirth
生完孩子要離婚再離婚
Why young people lack
為什麼年輕人缺乏
Motivation for marriage and childbirth
結婚生育動機
this is what everyone is asking
這大家都在問
Let's start with family experience
我們先從家庭經驗著手
Early Family Experiences for Adolescents
青少年早期家庭經驗
Regardless of childhood and adolescence
不管兒童期青少年期
Are the parents divorced?
父母有沒有離婚
In many Chinese families, the parents do not divorce
我們中國家庭很多是父母不離婚
but conflicting
可是有衝突的
parent-child conflict
還有親子關係衝突
Early experiences of adolescence
青少年期的早期經驗
Dating Behavior in Your Early Adulthood
對你成年初期的約會行為
what are the marriage expectations
婚姻期望是如何
especially in your 30s
尤其到了30多歲
We can talk about the actual act of marriage
我們可以講到實際的婚姻行為
usually tell you
一般來講會跟你說
His self-esteem comes first
他自尊第一
bad grades wait
成績不好等等
negative impact
負面衝擊
and always tell you
而且常常跟你說
will continue into adulthood
會延續到成年期
However, it is uncertain in the literature that
可是文獻上不確定的是
after parents divorce
父母離婚之後
Children are less willing to marry
孩子是比較不想結婚
Or get married early
還是反而提早結婚
Because if the child does not want to get married
因為孩子如果不想結婚
because he sees conflict
是因為他看到衝突
Seeing that the parent-child relationship is not good
看到父母親子關係不好
But some marry early
可是有些提早結婚
because he felt he needed a relationship
是因為他覺得他需要一個關係
He comes from a place where resources are relatively scarce
他來自資源比較缺乏的地方
He needs to get into marriage
他需要一進入婚姻
We pay special attention to this divorced family
這個離婚家庭我們特別著重
when he got divorced
他離婚的時間點
Over 13 years old or under 22 years old
13歲以上或是22歲以下
then go and see what's different
然後去看看有什麼不一樣
If parents divorced before the age of 13
父母在13歲之前離婚的話
Will affect pre-marital pregnancy of children
會影響子女婚前的懷孕
But it won't affect your early marriage
但是不會影響你的早婚
Parental conflict high in early teenage years
親少年初期父母衝突高
won't marry early
不會早婚
High parent-child conflict leads to early marriage
親子衝突高會早婚
is it clear
就很清楚了嘛
But cohabitation and pre-marital relationship
但有同居和婚前關係的
more likely to marry early
早婚可能性也高
If you are with a two-parent family
如果你跟雙親家庭
And the group with low conflict
而且衝突低的這一組來比
Parents' Early Divorce Experience
父母早期離婚經驗
lead to young adulthood
會導致年輕成年期
Negative effects of intimacy
親密關係的負面影響
then on the other hand
然後另外一方面
It is important to note that gender differences in the effect
很重要的是性別差異的效果
very obvious
非常的明顯
His family income was relatively high before he was young
他親少年前家庭收入比較高
good family relationship
家人之間關係好
And he currently has a job
而且他目前有工作的
He is more likely to be 28 years old
他比較可能在28歲
get married and give birth again
又結婚又生育
For women
對女性來講
If parents are divorced or separated
如果父母已經離婚或分居的
She is more likely to marry and have children
她比較可能又結婚又生育
but adolescence
可是青少年期
her family income is high
她家庭收入高
She currently has a job
她自己目前有工作的
she is less likely to marry
她比較不可能結婚
less likely to have children
也比較不可能生育
If girls are fine
女生如果精細能力高
Compared with those who do not think that there are married
比較沒有認為有結婚的
hope and desire
希望跟欲望
So what is the reflection of this thing for me?
所以這個東西給我的反思是什麼
Taiwanese family
台灣的家庭
In fact, many places
其實很多地方
Or the impact between tradition and modernity
還是在傳統跟現代之間的衝擊
compromise there
在那裡調和妥協
because of our values
因為我們的價值觀
between our actions
我們的行為之間
some are persistent
有一些是持續的
some are constant
有些是不變的
So if say Taiwan
所以如果說台灣
and East Asian society
還有東亞社會
We are different from Europe and the United States
我們跟歐美地區不一樣的地方
because you study a family in transition
在於你研究一個變遷中的家庭
Needs to go beyond your interpretation of personal resources
需要在你解釋個人資源之外
should also be considered
應該要同時考量
The interaction of cultural norms
文化規範的交互作用
Thank you Professor Yu
謝謝宇教授
Please talk about Yujiao
請講宇教
you
you